Good afternoon. Today's דף Daf is נ"ה, Nun Hey, 55. We're a
bit behind, so we pick up on the משנה Mishna נ"ד עמוד
ב', Nun Dalet Amud Bet, and we had a nice אגדתא Agadata
yesterday in the discussion of
lighting candles on ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur and then מוצאי
יום כיפור. Motzei Yom Kippur. Anyway, we will see that we have
some אגדתא Agadata coming up in the next coming דפים Dapim as
well. Let's take a look at the next issue that is addressed
in the context of מנהגים Minhagim on the משנה Mishna here, נ"ד
עמוד ב', Nun Dalet Amud Bet, near the top of the page.
מקום שנהגו לעשות מלאכה בתשעה באב עושין, Makom shenahagu laasot melacha b'tisha
b'av osin, a place where the custom is to allow, not specifically
to do but similar to ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, to allow מלאכה
Melacha to be done on תשעה באב Tisha B'av you can do
it. מקום שנהגו שלא לעשות מלאכה אין עושין, Makom shenahagu shelo laasot
melacha ein osin, place where that's not the custom you don't do
it. It's interesting, you know, because a person who's sitting שבעה Shiva
doesn't go out and do their job, but here actually, and many
ways of course, the אבל, Aveil, there's this whole theme of אבילות
Aveilut which intensifies up
through until תשעה באב, Tisha B'av, and the אבילות Aveilut becomes more
intense as it becomes closer and on תשעה באב Tisha B'av itself.
So it's interesting that there are different practices and it's not strictly
forbidden to do מלאכה. Melacha.
ובכל מקום תלמידי חכמים בטלים, Uv'chol makom talmidei chachamim batelim, and in
all places the תורה Torah sages or תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim, the
תורה Torah students, do not do מלאכה. Melacha. They spend the whole
day presumably
in קינות Kinnot or learning or related issues, immersed in the mourning.
Which as we know nowadays is true in the community as well,
that it's convenient when תשעה באב Tisha B'av falls out on a
Sunday and it is hard for most people who have a job
to take off yet another day after all of the ימים טובים
Yamim Tovim and so on, but there are definitely people who do
this and make a point
of devoting תשעה באב Tisha B'av to a day focused on the
mourning. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לעולם יעשה אדם עצמו תלמיד חכם,
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer l'olam yaaseh adam atzmo talmid chacham, a
person, at least for this particular הלכה Halacha but he says לעולם
L'olam so we'll see about that in the גמרא, Gemara, should always
see himself as a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham if it means putting
more stringencies upon yourself. Maybe not taking more privileges but at least
to be more stringent upon oneself.
So we'll see about that as well. Let's take a look at
the גמרא.
Gemara. תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham in the גמרא Gemara mean a master
of the תורה? Torah?
No, that's why I actually said it means a תלמיד. Talmid. I
corrected, I said it means a disciple, right. It means a תורה
Torah student.
Yeah, it doesn't have to be like you should treat yourself as
a huge גדול. Gadol. No, but from the class of people that
are like תורה Torah students and therefore, you know, look, we know
like for example in the ישיביש Yeshivishe world, people tend to be
more מחמיר Machmir on themselves. In some ways they have the inclination
and they also to some degree have also
what they're being taught, but it's also, you know, with all of
their entire time focused on religious pursuits, you know, that sort of
creates that type of an inclination but they also have the sometimes
they have the privilege and the opportunity to do it. It's like
fine, you know, you're not out there in the real world you
don't have a job that says if you don't show up today
you're getting fired. You know, so they have but that's a reality,
that's a reality today and I think it was somewhat of a
reality at that time as well. You're talking about a group of
people, not necessarily
huge גדולים, Gedolim, they're the students, the disciples of the חכמים, Chachamim,
but these were people that would more have this type of an
inclination, more have the opportunity I would say to follow it. Okay,
let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר שמואל אין תענית ציבור בבבל
אלא תשעה באב בלבד. Amar Shmuel ein taanit tzibur b'bavel ela tisha
b'av bilvad.
There is no תענית ציבור. Taanit Tzibur. Now תענית ציבור Taanit Tzibur
has a specific meaning if one learns מסכת תענית, Masechet Taanit, of
those series of fasts that one would do for the sake... for
the concerns about rain and it wasn't raining and they would grow
and it would be sort of short and then it would grow
until the point where it would be a full day fast and
it would lead to a lot of related practices: not doing מלאכה,
Melacha, having a, obviously, a full day fast, but also public prayer,
adding ברכות Brachot to the שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, you know, all
סליחות Slichot and so on. So he said that in
בבל, Bavel, רש"י Rashi explains it is that since בבל Bavel is
a place that as we know from many other times in the
גמרא Gemara is really not in need of rain and is a
very, you know, has a lot of water there, so you don't
have any... you never really have a day that's a true תענית
ציבור. Taanit Tzibur. And it's interesting what he means, meaning is it
just will never happen that you will have a need for this...
for a rain based fast, or even if it happens somehow categorically
בבל Bavel is seen as a different category. You know, it's not
Jewish... it's not the Jewish land. It's when you need rain in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that it warrants a fast. Even if it
would happen that you would need rain in בבל Bavel it would
not... maybe you would fast but it wouldn't warrant the status of
תענית ציבור. Taanit Tzibur. So one way or the other he is
saying that in בבל Bavel either it'll never happen that you'll need
a full blown תענית ציבור—like Taanit Tzibur obviously again you'll have the
historical fasts, you know, like we have for, you know, צום גדליה
Tzom Gedaliah and י"ז בתמוז—and Shiva Asar B'Tammuz you might fast occasionally
for rain, but it will never grow to the full weight of
a תענית ציבור. Taanit Tzibur. of a full-day fasting with all of
its stringencies, either because there will never be that need or because
fundamentally בבל *Bavel* doesn't warrant it. אלא *Ella*, the one example is
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av, בלבד *Tisha B'Av bilvad*. כי *Ki* תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av. *Tisha B'Av*, which is not based on rain, it is
the one day though that they will practice as a full תענית
ציבור Taanis Tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur*, because every all the other, you know,
historical fasts are not full days. תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av*
is a full day. So that is the one that will have
the laws of a full תענית ציבור Taanis Tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur*, but
you won't have it in the other historical fasts obviously and you
won't have it rain-based either. Okay, so let's see what the implications
of that of that of that statement is. למימרא *L'meimra*, that means
to say, דסבר שמואל Shmuel תשעה באב Tisha B'Av. בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashos שלו אסור asur, *d'savar Shmuel Tisha B'Av bein hashmashot shelo assur*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first assumes that the relevance of this
is, is that by calling something a תענית ציבור Taanis Tzibur *Ta'anit
Tzibbur*, it's a full day, and for a full day means that
you did that you begin it even before, you know, you know,
before the sunset, before בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos *bein hashmashot*. The בין
השמשות Bein Hashmashos *bein hashmashot* period has to be, you have to
treat לחומרא *l'chumra*. Okay, and we know we do that for שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat* and יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* and so on.
So the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* assumption is you do it for something that
has a full status of a תענית ציבור Taanis Tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur*
as well. So, and presumably that's what you're saying. והאמר שמואל Shmuel
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av. בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos שלו מותר mutar *Ve'ha'amar
Shmuel Tisha B'Av bein hashmashot shelo mutar*, but שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* himself
said that you could actually eat during בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos *bein
hashmashot* of תשעה *Tisha*. We know of course we don't, but this
is actually debated in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Can does תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av, *Tisha B'Av* begin only after בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos *bein
hashmashot* or do you have to stop fast start fasting even before
בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos. *bein hashmashot*? So which is it? וכי תימא
קסבר שמואל Shmuel כל תענית ציבור Taanis Tzibur. בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos
שלו מותר mutar *V'chi teima kasavar Shmuel kol Ta'anit Tzibbur bein hashmashot
shelo mutar*, maybe it's not a problem. Maybe he holds that that's
true about every תענית ציבור taanit tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur*. Every rain-based full-day
fast day begin you know you can eat during בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashos *bein hashmashot*, you know, it's all דרבנן *drabbanan*. Maybe בין השמשות
bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot* is allowed for all full-day fasts. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והאנן תנן *ve'ha'anan tenan*, but we taught in
the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, אוכלין ושותין מבעוד יום *ochlin v'shotin mib'od yom*,
that in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* by תענית taanit? *Ta'anit*, that when
you get to the full-blown status of it and it's a full
day, your eating and drinking has to be from the day before.
And מבעוד יום *mib'od yom* means when it's presumably definitely the day
before, which means that on a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur? *Ta'anit Tzibbur*
you stop eating before בין השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot*. למיעוטי מאי
*L'me'utei mai*, what did that come to exclude? לאו למיעוטי בין השמשות
bein hashmashot *Lav l'me'utei bein hashmashot*, isn't that telling you that on
a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur* you stop eating during the
even before בין השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot*? That you exclude בין
השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot* from the eating period? The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, לא Lo. *Lo*, not necessarily. למיעוטי משחשיכה *L'me'utei mishechashicha*, it's
coming to say that you don't eat once it's night, meaning it's
contrasting, what's the most obvious contrast between the other historical fasts? That
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* is contrasting the earlier rain-based fasts to the full-blown
תענית ציבור taanit tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibbur*. But if we were to make
a similar contrast between for us historical the historical fasts compared to
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av*, we'd say oh the historical fasts
those begin in the in the beginning of the day. תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av* begins already the night before. So we're not
coming to emphasize yes בין השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot* but not
בין השמשות bein hashmashot. *bein hashmashot*. I don't know about בין השמשות
*bein hashmashot*. The biggest difference is whether it starts in the morning
or does it start at the night. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying. Similarly there when it talks about the full-blown
תענית ציבור taanit tzibur. *Ta'anit Tzibbur* based for rain where it says
that it's that you stop eating the day before, it doesn't necessarily
address the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* issue. Maybe בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*
is מותר mutar *mutar*. But what it means is you can't eat
once it's night as opposed to the other types of the of
the the earlier rain fasts which are you can eat during the
nighttime. לא Lo למיעוטי משחשיכה *Lo, l'me'utei mishechashicha*, the only thing there
that's being emphasized is that once it gets to this full-blown stage,
you can't eat the night before either. Okay, so now we're saying
שמואל *Shmuel* says it's like a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur, *Ta'anit Tzibbur*
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av* has the full-blown status, but it
just so happens now that we've reconciled the statements of שמואל *Shmuel*,
that whether תענית ציבור taanit tzibur. *Ta'anit Tzibbur*, whether תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av. *Tisha B'Av*, you can eat בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. Okay, let's
take a look. נימא מסייעא ליה *Nima mesayei'a lei*, let's try to
give a proof to this. אין in, בין תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
ליום הכיפורים *Ein bein Tisha B'Av l'Yom HaKippurim*. There's a ברייתא Baita
*braita* that says the only difference between תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha
B'Av* and יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, which there's obviously a
lot of differences, אלא שזה ספקו אסור asur וזה ספקו מותר Seiko
Mutar *ella shezeh sefeiko assur v'zeh sefeiko mutar*. That one you can
eat during the doubtful period and the other the doubtful period is
forbidden. Now of course, as רש"י *Rashi* points out, there's a lot
of differences. On יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* if you eat,
you get כרת *karet*. On תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av*, you
know, you don't. It's forbidden. But it means לכתחילה *lechatchila* what you're
allowed to do, not בדיעבד *bedi'avad* what the consequences are. Even there,
of course, there's a difference between איסור Issur מלאכה melacha, *issur melacha*
and not איסור issur מלאכה melacha *issur melacha*. Okay, but anyway within
a narrow sense, if we're looking just at the the practice of
the fast day, the difference this ברייתא Braisa, *braita* says is the
period is the issue of ספק *safek*. So מאי ספקו מותר *mai
sefeiko mutar*, what does it mean the doubtful period is permitted on
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av*? לאו בין השמשות *Lav bein hashmashot*,
does it not mean בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*? So here a ברייתא
Beraita *braita* seems to be saying exactly שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* point, that not
the point that it's considered a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur, *Ta'anit Tzibbur*,
but the point that בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* is permissible. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לא lo. *Lo*, not necessarily. כי דאמר רב
Rav ששת בריה דרב אידי *Ki d'amar Rav Sheshet breih d'Rav Idi*,
maybe it's like Rav Sheshet breih d'Rav Idi said, לקביעא דירחא *likvi'ah
de'yarcha*, when it's coming to determine which day is ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh*. הכא נמי לקביעא דירחא *Hacha nami likvi'ah de'yarcha*, here
too regarding which day is ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh? *Rosh Chodesh*, which
means that on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av* that if you
genuinely, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says it's very clear, obviously we don't do
a ספק דיומא *safek de'yoma* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*,
right? We keep two days סוכות *Sukkot* and we keep two days
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* although that's actually... Of course we
do not keep two days יום כיפור. Yom Kippur That's not part
of a general practice of ספיקא דיומא Sfeika DeYoma for obvious reasons.
Okay, who's going to fast two days straight? Although as people do
know, during World War II, when מיר, Mir, the מיר ישיבה Mir
Yeshiva went to Shanghai and there was a whole questions about where
to draw the international date line, some people think the whole ישיבה,
Yeshiva, I actually know knew someone passed away like 30, 40 years
ago, whatever, but who was a student of the חפץ חיים Chofetz
Chaim who was actually at the מיר ישיבה Mir Yeshiva when it
was in Shanghai, and he said it was only like some יחידי
סגולה, Yechidei Segula, but a few people at least in the ישיבה
Yeshiva were מחמיר Machmir because they didn't know there's a question where
to draw the international date line and they kept two days of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur. and they really fasted for two full days
straight. Okay, but there's obvious reasons why with exception such as those
we don't do ספיקא דיומא Sfeika DeYoma by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur
But let's say says the גמרא Gemara you genuinely forget ספיקא דיומא
Sfeika DeYoma forget nowadays we pretend as if you don't know. You
really lived in the times of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
you genuinely didn't know which day was ראש חודש, ראש השנה. In
that case you'd have to keep two days of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur. but if such a thing were to happen by תשעה באב,
Tisha B'Av. of course it's a little funny because if there is
a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and we're doing a real קידוש החודש
Kiddush HaChodesh then you're not doing תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av But if
there's a period with
regardless you'll never wind up keeping two days of תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av? whether there's a real doubt or not a real doubt. So
that's what ספקו מותר means but not בין השמשות which is a
pretty weak answer because that's a very strange hypothetical. Yes, sir?
Isn't there a גמרא Gemara about the two days of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. and the גמרא Gemara then concludes that you should eat
a
יום טוב'דיג Yom Tov'dig סעודת מפסקת Seudas Mafsekes כאילו Ke'ilu you fasted
those two days?
The גמרא Gemara asks that in the meaning of the פסוק Pasuk
that says בתשעה לחודש בערב מערב עד ערב, BeTisha LaChodesh BaErev MeErev
Ad Erev, וכי בתשעה מתעני ולא
בעשירי מתעני אלא כל. V'chi BeTisha Misani V'lo BaAsiri Misani Ella Kol.
Right, fine.
So there is already underlined so that might be a rationale on
the hermeneutic but they had some sense that it was two days.
That כאילו, Ke'ilu, oh that's interesting that
that כאילו, Ke'ilu, yes, but certainly to say that you halachically fast
two days straight, right, anyway. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
But we're trying to use to get out of the simple sense
of that ברייתא Beraita which is that you actually are allowed to
eat on בין השמשות of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av Okay, by the
way, you might be surprised to hear that there's a genuine debate
with the ראשונים Rishonim how we פוסקן Pasken about that, about whether
you can eat בין השמשות of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av Of course,
of course we obviously פוסקן Pasken that you don't.
Going in and going out?
No, going in, that you might based on how we פוסקן Pasken
about this. Okay, anyway, דרש רבא. Darsh Rava. So רבא Rava expounded.
עוברות ומניקות מתענות ומשלימות בו, Uberos U-Menikos Misanos U-Mashlimos Bo, pregnant women
and nursing
and nursing women have to fast and do a full fast on
תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av right? There's a lot of leniencies about the
minor historical fast days, but on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av they have
a full fast כדרך שמתענות ומשלימות ביום הכיפורים Kederech She-Misanos U-Mashlimos Be-Yom
HaKippurim just like on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur
Now, obviously a just like we don't want to get to issues
well actually look it's an interesting question which I'm not going to
get to right now which is that by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
you needed to really to get to a level of סכנה. Sakana.
We know by the minor fast days that even things like just
a pregnant woman סתם Stam and even if it's just like חולה
כל הגוף Choleh Kol Ha-Guf like on the minor fast days you
don't fast. In תשעה באב Tisha B'Av what is it's not the
low threshold of the minor fast days, but do you need it
to literally get to the place of סכנה? Sakana? Is there some
middle level threshold? Okay, that's like a that's a discussion. But anyway,
but here it says at least at least as a general rule
they fast they fast fully just like they would on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur.
I thought the משנה Mishnah in יומא Yoma says a pregnant woman
can decide if she needs to eat on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur Yes, right, right, right. When she feels that she needs
to eat, but it's not just she סתם Stam feels that she's
got oh my god I've got this yen for pickles and ice
cream type of thing. It would have to be she feels she
needs to eat because of a concern of her health, right, and
serious concern of health. We go by what he says but it's
if she's telling us something that's related to not just pickles.
Right.
It's related to a concern of a סכנה Sakana type of a
concern. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, now, ובין
השמשות שלו
אסור. U-Bein Hashmashos Shelo Assur. So there it says and so רבא
Rava says he ended by saying it's like יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
that בין השמשות is forbidden. So רבא Rava disagreed with שמואל and
says that תשעה באב Tisha B'Av בין השמשות is forbidden. וכן אמר
משמיה דרבי יוחנן V'chen Ama Mishme De-Rabbi Yochanan and they said the
same in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that בין השמשות
is forbidden on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av, So גמרא Gemara says ומי
אמר רבי יוחנן הכי U-Mi Amar Rabbi Yochanan Hachi did רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan really say that? ואמר רבי יוחנן תשעה באב אינו כתענית
ציבור, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan Tisha B'Av Eino K'Taanis Tzibur, תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av, does not have the weight of תענית ציבור taanit tzibur. and
we know that when שמואל said it is like תענית ציבור taanit
tzibur the immediate assumption the גמרא Gemara said was that the equation
was to emphasize the איסור issur, of בין השמשות. So if רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that it's not like תענית ציבור taanit
tzibur presumably he means תענית ציבור taanit tzibur you can't eat בין
השמשות but תשעה באב Tisha B'Av. you can. מאי לאו לבין השמשות?
Mai Lav L'Bein Hashmashos? Does that not mean that he's saying that
בין השמשות is the different? So therefore he's so he might agree
that
תענית ציבור. Taanit Tzibur, is off, but תשעה באב seems to be
okay. But says לא למלאכה, Lo l'melacha, no, relating to מלאכה, melacha.
you don't do מלאכה Melacha on תענית ציבור Taanit Tzibur, and here
he's telling you that on תשעה באב you're allowed to. Yes, our
משנה Mishnah tells you there are different מנהגים, minhagim, but in principle
you're allowed to do מלאכה. melacha.
You're more strict on תשעה באב than a regular תענית?
Taanit Well, we'll see there are ways it's more strict, but now
we're emphasizing ways it's less strict. So the גמרא Gemara says: מלאכה
תנינא. Melacha tanina. מלאכה melacha. we taught in a משנה. Mishnah מקום
שנהגו לעשות מלאכה בתשעה באב עושים. Makom shenahagu laasot melacha beTisha B'Av
osim. מקום שנהגו שלא לעשות אין עושים. Makom shenahagu shelo laasot ein
osim. ואפילו רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Ve'afilu Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, even
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who ends the משנה
Mishnah, by saying everybody should act like, you know, like disciples of
the sages, לא אמר אלא דכי יתיב ולא עביד לא מיחזי כיוהרא.
Lo amar ela deki yativ velo avid la mechezi kiyuhara. All he's
saying is that you,
you know, it's okay to not do מלאכה. melacha. It won't look
like you're, like you're being like, what's the good English word for
יוהרא? yuhara? Religious airs, but there's a better word for it. Anyway,
ostentatious religious behavior, you know, it doesn't look like you're being a
religious show-off because you're just sitting and not doing מלאכה. melacha Right?
Yes, right. Sanctimony. But anyway, but yes, so that's acceptable not to
do מלאכה. melacha. But that means it's acceptable as a practice, as
a מנהג. minhag. It doesn't mean that there's a, it's strictly forbidden.
אבל מיתסר לא אסר. Aval meitsar lo assar. Nobody's actually forbidding מלאכה
melacha on תשעה באב. So you don't need רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
to point out that on תשעה באב you can technically do מלאכה.
melacha. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא מאי אינו כתענית ציבור? Ela
mai eino k'taanit tzibur? Fine. So what does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
mean that it's not like a תענית taanit ציבור? He means
לתפילת נעילה. L'tefillat ne'ila. That you don't say נעילה. ne'ila. That we
think נעילה ne'ila is just something just for יום כיפור Yom Kippur.
because we don't experience it in our year other than יום כיפור.
But in the משניות mishnayot in תענית ta'anis, we find out that
when they had a תענית ta'anis ציבור for rain, they would add
an extra תפילה, tefillah, they would add to the תפילה tefillah which...
I mean sometimes they actually do תענית in ישראל. Yisrael.
I mean
they have תעניות taaniyot but they never get... but I don't think
they make them full day fasts and they never get... there's a
whole progression until you get to a full-blown...
Yeah. We're leaning towards the end because of ראש חודש?
Yeah, yeah. So it is, yeah, that's what
תענית ציבור here does not mean the early stages. That's why I've
always been saying the full-blown. It's after you go through a series
of cycles of smaller fasts and you still don't have rain and
it's later and later in the year, then you do the full-blown
תענית ציבור. So that's the difference. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says:
דהאמר רבי יוחנן. Deha'amar Rabbi Yochanan.
Would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say that you don't do נעילה ne'ila
on תשעה באב? Doesn't רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say: ולואי שיתפלל אדם
והולך כל היום כולו? Ul'vai sheyitpalel adam veholech kol hayom kulo? That
were only that a person would דאוון daven the entire day. Meaning
that there's no problem of doing an extra תפילה. tefillah. You can
do a תפילת נדבה. tefillat nedava. תוספות discusses: can you סתם stam
do an extra one, do you have to have a reason, do
you have to add something to make it a little different? But
nevertheless רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan fundamentally is in the principle that you're
not restricted from adding תפילות. tefillot. So the גמרא Gemara. gives the
obvious answer: התם חובה הכא רשות. Hatam chova hacha reshut.
No, there, meaning by תענית ציבור, it's an obligation to add נעילה.
ne'ila. If you סתם stam want to add a נעילה ne'ila today
on תשעה באב or on any day, געזונט אהייט, gezunt aheit, but
the idea that there's an obligation, that the liturgy is, you know,
four תפילות tefillot today and not three, that is only on תענית
ציבור. So what have we said until now? שמואל equates תשעה באב
to תענית ציבור, but the גמרא Gemara has not told you what
the implication of that equation is because it's actually said that they're
both lenient according to שמואל in the way that בין השמשות is
permissible. רב Rav? said... was it רב? רבא Rava said. רבא Rava
said, thank you. רבא Rava said that תשעה באב בין השמשות is
forbidden, and he actually emphasized the stringencies of it comparing it to
יום כיפור even for the laws of a pregnant and nursing women.
So he said בין השמשות is forbidden. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
that תשעה באב is not like תענית ציבור. What is the difference?
It might be to say one for בין השמשות is forbidden, תשעה
באב בין השמשות is permitted. Or it might be this other point
here, a more point about the liturgy and about saying נעילה. ne'ila.
So you have a range... a collection of different positions about בין
השמשות for תשעה באב and תענית ציבור where clearly תענית ציבור is
the more likely candidate for it being forbidden, but it could be
that they're both forbidden. Yes.
So the נעילה ne'ila is not a genre of תפילה tefillah unique
to יום כיפור, but it is a genre, a liturgical genre of
asking, petitioning for רחמים rachamim at the end of a fast when
a fast is called for and that fits a...
And when the nature of the fast is as opposed to the
historical fast, which is more about the past, when the nature of
the fast is very much focused on petition, I would say. You
know, so therefore you use this final opportunity of נעילה ne'ila for
one final opportunity for, right, beseeching and רחמים rachamim and petition. So
that is like the fasts of rain when they are full-blown and
יום כיפור. That is correct. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: איבעית אימא. Iba'it eima. מאי אינו כתענית ציבור? Mai eino k'taanit
tzibur? Maybe here's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan meant to distinguish it
from תענית ציבור if it's not the בין השמשות. לעשרים וארבע *L'esrim
v'arba*, a similar liturgical difference that on a fast day you add
six other ברכות *brachot* to the שמונה עשרה *Shmoneh Esreh* and it
becomes not the שמונה עשרה *Shmoneh Esreh* but the twenty-four. And all
those ברכות *brachot* are again, of different ברכות *brachot* of רחמים *rachamim*
and בקשה *bakasha*. And that you do not do on תשעה באב
*Tisha B'Av*. So a same type of answer about liturgical difference. רב
פפא אמר *Rav Pappa amar*: מאי אינו כתענית ציבור *mai i'no catanit
tzibur*, what does it mean it's not like a תענית ציבור *taneet
tzibur*? אינו כראשונות אלא כאחרונות *Ino k'rishonot ella k'achronot*. So he totally
takes the punch out of the statement. It's not like the earlier
fast days which we have not been calling תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur*
at this stage, the smaller rain-based fasts, but it's like the last
rain, the end of the cycle where it is full-blown, it starts
the night before and בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* is אסור asur *assur*.
So that's a way to reinterpret רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* to get
him to say what רבא *Rava* was saying, that בין השמשות *bein
hashmashot* is forbidden, ואסורה *v'asura*, and it's forbidden. מיתיבי *Meitivei*, they ask
on this: אין בין תשעה באב ליום הכיפורים אלא שזה ספקו אסור
וזה ספקו מותר *Ein bein Tisha B'Av l'Yom HaKippurim ella shezeh sefeko
assur v'zeh sefeko mutar*. We have a ברייתא Beraita. *beraita* which is
along the lines of what we said before. There is no difference
between תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* and יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. It is
what we said before. There is no difference between תשעה באב *Tisha
B'Av* and יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* but the difference of ספק *safek*.
מאי ספקו מותר *Mai sefeko mutar*, what does ספק *safek* mean? לאו
בין השמשות שלו *Lav bein hashmashot shelo*? So it's basically this is
what we already alluded to earlier. Does that not show you that
בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* is permissible during תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*? אמר
רב ששת amar Rav Sheshes בריה דרב אידי *Amar Rav Sheshet brei
d'Rav Idi*: לא לקביעא דירחא *lo, l'kavia d'yarcha*. No, it means if
you ממש mamash *mamash* don't know which day is ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh*, then you have real trouble for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* but
not for תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now
says: הכל לכל דברים זה וזה שווים *Ha'l'chol devarim zeh v'zeh shavin*?
Is it so? It sounds like for all other things, whatever the
ספק *safek* means aside, the practices are the same. What does it
mean that the practices
are
the same? So מסייע לרבי אלעזר *Mesaye l'Rabbi Elazar*, that supports רבי
אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. דאמר רבי אלעזר *D'amar Rabbi Elazar*: אסור לו לאדם
שיושיט אצבעו במים בתשעה באב *assur lo l'adam she'yoshit etzba'o b'mayim b'Tisha
B'Av*. How, what constitutes the prohibition of washing or bathing on תשעה
באב *Tisha B'Av* and on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? Is it even,
is it only pleasure-based? So would it or even any type of
bathing? So we're very... so according to him we're very strict on
תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* like we are on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*.
You can't even stick your pinky into water, כדרך שאסור לו להושיט
אצבעו ביום הכיפורים *k'derech she'assur lo l'hoshit etzba'o b'Yom HaKippurim*, the same
way it is forbidden on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So that's supported
by and it would not be the same on a תענית ציבור
*taneet tzibur*. תענית ציבור *Taneet tzibur* we actually allow you to do
פניו ידיו ורגליו *panav yadav v'raglav*. We allow you to do your
face and your feet, and this of course was in hot desert
places and walking barefoot or in sandals, and your hands. We are
much more lenient in terms of a type of a bathing that
is not clearly indulgent bathing. But on תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* and
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* we are much stricter. So that is supported
by this ברייתא braita *beraita* that equates תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* to
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*.
Meaning he could have also said about wearing leather shoes or something
like that, right? You just chose this example.
Yeah, well no because on the תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur* those are
also...
Not allowed to wear leather shoes in the other one?
The נעילת הסנדל *ne'ilat hasandel* I believe is also allowed on the
others as well, but the difference is that תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*
on the one hand is not just because of its תענית *taneet*
dimension, but also because of its אבילות aveilus, *aveilus* dimension is one
thing to remember about תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*. There are two dimensions.
The fasting is not אבילות aveilus. *aveilus* based, but some of the
other things about מלאכה melacha, *melacha* is interesting that doesn't fall in
that category, but other things about learning תורה *Torah* etc. are clearly
אבילות *aveilus* based, and things like bathing and רחיצה *rechitza* whatever have
both components to them. So I understand what you're saying, and יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* is all the fasting based, but obviously it's much
weightier than other types of things. But yes, in terms of the
other תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur*, I believe that the other things like
that are fasting based are... I understand what you're saying. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. Well no, again what we're calling תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur* is
not minor historical fasts, it's not minor rain-based days, it's when you
get to the rain-based in the learning מסכת Masechet תענית *Masechet Taneet*
and you get to the full-blown fast based on rain. Okay, so
anyways so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. So you see,
there you see the comparison that even what constitutes bathing is the
same for those. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, כדרך שאסור לו
להושיט אצבעו ביום הכיפורים *k'derech she'assur lo l'hoshit etzba'o b'Yom HaKippurim*. מיתיבי
*Meitivei*, I ask on this: אין בין תשעה באב לתענית ציבור אלא
שזה אסור בעשיית מלאכה melacha וזה מותר בעשיית מלאכה melachah *Ein bein
Tisha B'Av l'taneet tzibur ella shezeh assur b'asiyat melacha v'zeh mutar b'asiyat
melacha*. We have another ברייתא braita: *beraita* that says that the difference
is whether you can do מלאכה melachah, *melacha* or not. That technically
you're allowed to do מלאכה melachah *melacha* on תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*,
but you cannot do it on תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur*. And therefore
now we are finally... so again we're seeing a way in which
תענית ציבור *taneet tzibur* is stricter, right, than תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*
like the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* discussion. Okay, במקום שנהגו *B'makom shenahagu*,
in a place where they allow מלאכה melacha *melacha* on תשעה באב
*Tisha B'Av*. So why is that a question? הכל לכל דברים זה
וזה שווים *Ha'l'chol devarim zeh v'zeh shavin*? Because that suggests the other
practices are the same. Right? There are three models. It's an interesting
thing about it. There's יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* which is about fasting,
but it's connected, it could be based on a בקשה *bakasha* and
that way similar to fasting on rain, certainly stricter, it's biblical, but
also we should remember that an element of fasting on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* might be based on... nothing to do with בקשה *bakasha*.
According to some it has to do with sort of the sense
of, like the רמב״ם *Rambam* phrases it, he says it's שבת שבתון
*Shabbat Shabbaton*. It's שביתה *shevita* from מלאכה melacha *melacha* and שביתה *shevita*
from אכילה *achila*. So not based on like the sense of being
miserable and בקשה *bakasha*, but a sense of freeing yourself from this
world. You know, so there could be other elements of fasting on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* has its own dimension. You
have fasting of תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* which is rain based which
is clearly בקשה *bakasha*. And you have תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* and
you have תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* which is historical, not just based
on בקשה *bakasha* for the future. So fasting as a and therefore
it's a fasting also that has a mourning component and an אבילות
*aveilut* component as well. So each one of these three things has
different qualities to them which might lead to different nuances in some
of their practices. Okay, so on תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* you don't
do מלאכה melacha. *melacha* because presumably you need everybody there focused in
the street praying all together as a ציבור *tzibur* for rain and
coming to God as an entire community and saying God we need
rain. תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* is more historical and past based and
therefore there's different practices about you know about the איסור מלאכה melacha
*issur melacha*. It's not that same pressing בקשה *bakasha* as you have
in a תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur*. On the other hand, it does
have אבילות *aveilut* components which should warrant an איסור מלאכה melacha *issur
melacha*. Anyway, so here the ברייתא braita *braita* is saying that on
the one ברייתא *braita* compared it to יום כיפורים *Yom Kippurim* and
this ברייתא *braita* is comparing it to תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur*. It
says with the exception of מלאכה melacha
*melacha*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on, two lines on
the bottom: הלכו דבריהם *halchu divreihem* so for other things זה וזה
שווים *zeh v'zeh shavim* תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* and תענית ציבור *Ta'anit
Tzibur* are the same. ואילו גבי תענית ציבור *v'ilu gabi Ta'anit Tzibur*
and by תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* up until now it's been always
stricter. No מלאכה melacha *melacha*, clearly forbidden בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. Regarding
bathing practices, it's more lenient. ואילו גבי תענית ציבור תניא *v'ilu gabi
Ta'anit Tzibur tanya*, כשאמרו אסור ברחיצה *keshe'amru assur b'rechitza*, when they say
you can't bathe on תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur*, לא אמרו אלא כל
גופו *lo amru ela kol gufo*, it's only your entire body. אבל
פניו ידיו ורגליו לא *aval panav yadav v'raglav lo*, but your face,
hands and feet are allowed. Okay, and if תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*
is being compared to תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur*, presumably it's more lenient
in the bathing practice. So which way do you go? Do you
compare it to יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* where even your pinky is
forbidden or do you compare it to תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* where
your hands and face are permissible? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אמר רב פפא תנא tana, קולי קולי קתני *amar Rav Papa tana
kulei kulei katani*. So the תנא *tana* is talking about the ways
in which תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* is more lenient. It's more lenient
than יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* in that you can do מלאכה melacha
*melacha*. It's more lenient than תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* in that you
can—no, did I say that wrong? No, in that yeah, in both
of them it's that you can do מלאכה melacha *melacha*, right? What
is the one by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* compared to? No,
ספק *safek*. It's more lenient than יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* in that
ספק *safek* is permitted. Maybe it means תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*, maybe
it means בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, maybe it means you don't know
which day is ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*. Okay. It's more lenient than
תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* in that you can do מלאכה melacha, *melacha*.
So there are two ways in which תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* has
leniencies, right? So it's lenient, more lenient than יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
for ספק *safek*, more lenient than תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* for the
איסור מלאכה melacha *issur melacha*. But there might be ways in which
it's more stringent than some of those. And yes, למעשה *l'ma'aseh*, at
least according to this approach, תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* is more strict
than תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* in terms of the bathing issue. And
in that way, it's more like יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So what
do we have? I know it's a little bit confusing with these
three different models. But basically, what you've got is the following: is
that תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* is אסור במלאכה *assur b'melacha* and it's—and
it's at least according to most positions here other than שמואל *Shmuel*,
it's אסור בין השמשות *assur bein hashmashot*, okay? That's תענית ציבור *Ta'anit
Tzibur*. But bathing is actually more lenient by תענית ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur*.
Where does תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* fall out? Well, תשעה באב *Tisha
B'Av* is debated about how it relates to the בין השמשות *bein
hashmashot*, maybe it's מותר *mutar*, maybe it's אסור בין השמשות *assur bein
hashmashot*. It's certainly more lenient in terms of that you can do
מלאכה melacha *melacha*, okay, for and במקום שנהגו *b'makom shenahagu* even if
it's not, it's only a מנהג minhag *minhag*. And in the bathing,
it's actually more strict. Okay, so that's why it's not like a
straight continuum. Different things have different factors, right? The איסור מלאכה melacha
*issur melacha* like I said might be making sure everybody's gathering in
the streets and praying for rain and we're all together, we're not
doing any other things. Okay, so in that way, תשעה באב *Tisha
B'Av* is more lenient. But in terms of the bathing, that might
have another aspect of אבילות *aveilut* component or, you know, that's more
strict and therefore תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* is more strict than תענית
ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* as far as the bathing is concerned. Okay, so
those are the ways different ways in which it relates. And certainly
it's more lenient than יום הכיפורים *Yom HaKippurim* in terms of this
issue of ספק *safek* which again might mean the בין השמשות *bein
hashmashot* issue. Yes, I still don't understand why we would be more
lenient in מלאכה melacha *melacha*. I understand that you're saying in תענית
ציבור *Ta'anit Tzibur* you want everyone focused on petitioning for rain or
whatever it is. So why can't you say the same thing? Shouldn't
everyone focus on the אבילות *aveilut* and not... Okay, but again, there
are lines, there are, you know, it's a question about past versus
an urgent... you know, what you—you know what they tell you in
business? You gotta make a chart of all your to-dos, you know,
and it's urgent and not urgent and important and not important, right?
So some things are very urgent and not important and some things
are whatever. Okay, so you know תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*... תשעה באב
doesn't have the same urgency as תענית ציבור, right?
It might be very important and it's אבילות, you know, it's אבילות
דרבים aveilus derabbim and all these things, so we do a lot
of things, we fast the whole day and
we say קינות kinos and all of this, but it's not the
same urgency as the תענית ציבור, so getting everybody here and everybody
petitioning whatever, there's degrees. Look, the reality is that, you know, think
about like the... anyway, like the איסור תפילין, issur tefillin, right? which
is on the first day of אבילות. We don't apply that on
all of תשעה באב, only on part of it. So again, you
know, not everything do we do to an extreme. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ובכל מקום תלמידי חכמים. u'vechol makom talmidei
chachamim. Now תלמידי talmidei and every place the disciples are strict and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says everybody should try
to act that way. וממדרבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר, U'mimad'Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel savar, this suggests רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
is of the opinion לא חיישינן ליוהרא, lo chashinan l'yuhara, we're not
concerned for יוהרא. yuhara. יוהרא yuhara means like a religious showing off,
like acting firmer than your station or warrants. Okay, so, you know
the joke like looker walks off the street and thinks he's a
גורנישט. gornisht. So anyway, okay, so anyway ורבנן סברי חיישינן ליוהרא, ve'rabbanan
savrei chashinan l'yuhara, and the rabbis say no, only Torah sages should
do it, or Torah disciples, not other people. Okay, והאיפכא שמעינן להו,
v'ha'ipcha sham'inan lehu, but we've heard that they adopt other positions. דתנן
ותניא נמי, d'tenan v'tanya nami, חתן אם ירצה לקרוא קריאת שמע לילה
הראשון קורא. chassan im yirtzeh likros krias shema lailah harishon korei. If
a groom wants to... the הלכה halacha is that a groom is
exempt on the first night from קריאת שמע krias shema because his
mind is too distracted, the first night of the wedding night. But
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says if he wants to be strict
and read קריאת שמע krias shema he can read it. ורבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר לא כל הרוצה ליטול את השם יטול, ve'Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer lo kol harotzeh litol es hashem yitol, not everybody
who wants to take God's name should be entitled to. If you
don't have the right כוונה kavanah and you're not at a level
that you can free yourself from distraction, you should not do it.
Now of course the background of this is it had earlier in
the משנה Mishnah. we had just read that רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's father did not read
קריאת... read קריאת שמע krias shema, the night that he got married.
Okay, so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is basically
saying not everybody is as holy as my father. Okay,
so not everybody can act as if they're able to have כוונה.
kavanah. By the way, nowadays we don't, we just פסקן pasken everybody
reads because nobody has enough כוונה kavanah even during the rest of
the time. Anyway, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so
you see רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is concerned
about acting like religious, you know, you know type of religious ostentatiousness,
ostentatiousness. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי יוחנן מוחלפת השיטה, amar
Rabi Yochanan muchelefes hashita, fine, reverse the positions. Presumably reverse the positions
in our משנה Mishnah. because there it makes sense what רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel was saying. So רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is the one that doesn't like you
acting that way if you're not at that level. ורב ששת בריה
דרב אידי אמר לא תיהפך, ve'Rav Sheshes breih de'Rav Idi amar lo
tehafech, you should not reverse the positions. There's ways to explain the
differences. דרבנן אדרבנן לא קשיא, d'rabbanan ad'rabbanan lo kashya, the rabbis that
here are, don't want you acting that way and there are okay
with it, that's not difficult. Why? הכא כיון דכולי עלמא עבדי מלאכה,
hacha kivan de'kulei alma avdi melacha,
because here if you're in a city where everybody is doing מלאכה
melacha. on תשעה באב, ואיהו לא עביד ve'ihu lo avid and you're
not doing it, מחזי כיוהרא, mechazi k'yuhara, it looks like you're showing
off. Oh, look how frum you are, you're not doing מלאכה. melacha
Okay, that's the other argument which we'll get to, but at least
you're acting different from the way everybody else is acting and therefore
you stand out and that's a problem. אבל התם, aval hasam, by
קריאת שמע, krias shema. כיון דכולי עלמא קרי, kivan de'kulei alma karei,
what's everybody else doing tonight? They're saying קריאת שמע. krias shema, ואיהו
קרי נמי קרי ve'ihu karei nami karei and you're also saying קריאת
שמע, krias shema so you're not acting different than everybody. You're acting
just like everybody else. You're not, you're not taking an exception. But
your practices therefore are the same as what everybody else is doing,
so לא מחזי כיוהרא, lo mechazi k'yuhara, you don't stand out, you
don't look and it's not showing off. So that's how they explain
that difference. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אדרבן שמעון בן גמליאל לא קשיא,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ad'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel lo kashya, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is not difficult also. התם הוא
דבעינן כוונה, hasam hu d'ba'inan kavanah,
there by the קריאת שמע you need to have, you know, ability
to focus and intent. ואנן סהדי דלא מצי כיוון דעתיה ve'anan sahadi
d'lo matzi kavein dateih and we know that, you know, that a
normal person cannot focus and therefore מחזי כיוהרא, mechazi k'yuhara, so anybody
who sees him reading even though other people are reading, people know
that he's a חתן chassan tonight. So everybody says, oh look what
such a big shot, he thinks he can have כוונה kavanah during
דאוונען, davening, you know, you know on his wedding night and there's
an obvious sense there that you're, you know, acting like a... like
in a way that's inappropriate. אבל הכא לא מחזי כיוהרא, aval hacha
lo mechazi k'yuhara, here it doesn't appear that way. אמר מלאכה הוא
דלית ליה, amar melacha hu d'leis leih, they say, yeah he's not
acting, he's not doing מלאכה, melacha but it's not because he's so
frum that he thinks he can't do מלאכה melacha. on תשעה באב.
He just doesn't have a job, he doesn't have work today. פוק
חזי כמה בטלני איכא בשוקא, puk chazi kamma batlanei ika b'shuka, go
look, go outside and look all of these, you know, you know,
all of these people out in the, in the street that are
wasting time, don't have anything to do. You know sometimes it's true
because like, like
sometimes because of my schedule, you know, I have a more academic
schedule so I'll be a little bit, so during like the summer
certainly I'll be a little free during the day and I'll go
outside and I'll say what are all these people doing out today?
Don't these people have work? I don't have work but what about
these people? Anyway, so outside there are a lot of people sometimes
that don't have work and who knows, they're out there in the
street. All right, anyway, so that's different ways of measuring the יוהרא.
yuhara. It is interesting to ask what is חז"ל's Chazal's concern about...
יוהרה, yuhara, right? Or what's sometimes like in our משנה, Mishnah, רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, everybody should make themselves like it. You know, it's
a tension between type of like pushing yourself religious or religious striving
and trying to sort of see a level that you want and
maybe I'm not yet, you know, there's a lot of things I
do wrong, but we should encourage my desires, you know, even if
it's a חומרא, chumra, there are things that I'm ממש being עובר
over on. So why should I be doing חומרות? chumrot? But you
know, on the one hand, maybe it's a way in which encourages
a religious striving and pushing yourself and it could be good. On
the other hand, A, what you see here is there's a concern
about communal perception, like every you know, people will sort of look
at you askance, like who are you? You don't do that and
you're doing this and whatever and you'll look like the show-off and
it'll be a problem in terms of the community. And also might
be a problem just in terms of myself because it allows me
to convince myself how
פרום frum I am, because you know I wear a black hat
and I wear a גארטל gartel and I do all this type
of stuff and I do מים אחרונים mayim acharonim and it allows
me to ignore the stuff that I really have to be working
on. So I think it's an interesting question about the issue about
the יוהרה. yuhara. Do you tolerate it? Do you encourage certain activities?
Do you actually discourage them? It's a real issue. Okay, let's take
a look now as we go on to the next משנה. Mishnah,
We finally return after that fascinating little survey of different places and
different מנהגים minhagim to the issue about the מנהג minhag. of
doing מלאכה melacha on ערב פסח Erev Pesach in the morning. From
חצות Chatzot on, nobody does it, but the question is in the
morning. So וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim omrim, the Sages say, it's a little
interesting the וחכמים, ve-Chachamim, right? He just blasts off in the middle
of a sentence. It connects really back to the first משנה. Mishnah
Why is that? I don't know, and because we wanted to talk
about מקום שנהגו. makom she-nahagu. וחכמים אומרים ve-Chachamim omrim and the Sages
say, ביהודה היו עושים מלאכה בערבי פסחים עד חצות ובגליל לא היו
עושים כל עיקר. Bi-Yehudah hayu osim melachah be-arvei Pesachim ad Chatzot u-va-Galil
lo hayu osim kol ikar. That this difference played out between יהודה
Yehudah and גליל. Galil. In יהודה, Yehudah, in Judea, right? They would
do it, they would do מלאכה, melacha. in the גליל Galil they
would not, and in the morning. Now, הלילה, ha-laylah, what about the
night before? Presumably in גליל Galil or in places that don't do
מלאכה melacha, in the morning, does it even begin the night before?
So בית שמאי אוסרים ובית הלל מתירים עד הנץ החמה. Beit Shammai
osrim u-Veit Hillel matirin ad hanetz hachamah. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
it begins even the night before, it's forbidden the night before, and
בית הלל Beit Hillel says no, it's allowed until daybreak, until sunrise.
Now the phrase of אוסרין osrin and מתירין matirin is very strange,
since until now we've only been talking about מנהג. minhag So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: מעיקרא תני מנהגא. me-ikara tani minhaga. So initially you were
talking about what the מנהג minhag is, ובסוף תני איסורא. u-ve-sof tani
issura. And now you're talking about אוסרין, osrin, מתירין, matirin, what's going
on? Is it a מנהג minhag or is it an actual דין?
din? אמר רבי יוחנן לא קשיא הא רבי מאיר הא רבי יהודה.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan lo kashya ha Rabbi Meir ha Rabbi Yehuda. It's
a difference between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
as whether actually it's a מנהג minhag or it's actually a הלכה.
halachah. דתניא, de-tanya, ותני ברייתא, ve-tani Braisa, אמר רבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi
Yehuda. So now we're finding out that the author of this משנה,
mishna. of the beginning of the משנה, Mishna. is רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. ביהודה היו עושים מלאכה בערבי פסחים עד חצות ובגליל אינם עושים
כל עיקר. Bi-Yehudah hayu osim melachah be-arvei Pesachim ad Chatzot u-va-Galil einam
osim kol ikar. So there this was a difference of יהודה Yehudah
and גליל. Galil. אמר לו רבי מאיר, Amar lo Rabbi Meir, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said to him, מה ראיה יהודה וגליל לכאן? mah
re'ayah Yehudah ve-Galil le-kan? What do I care about יהודה Yehudah and
גליל? Galil? What are you bringing it as relevant to how I
should practice where I live? You know, the הלכה halachah is אלא
מקום שנהגו לעשות מלאכה עושים מקום שנהגו שלא לעשות אין עושים. ela
makom she-nahagu la'asot melachah osim makom she-nahagu she-lo la'asot ein osim. It's
just every place goes, you go by, you look at what your
מנהג minhag, of your place is and that's what you do. What
difference does it make what they do in יהודה, Yehudah, what they
do in גליל? Galil? Now of course you could have just thought
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was giving a nice illustration of a
reality of different practices. But the גמרא Gemara is trying to figure
out, it sounds like they're debating. So what are they debating? So
the גמרא Gemara says: מדקאמר רבי מאיר מנהגא. mi-de-ka-amar Rabbi Meir minhaga.
Since רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is emphasizing, look, it's just a מנהג,
minhag. you look at your מנהג. minhag, מכלל דרבי יהודה איסורא קאמר.
mi-klal de-Rabbi Yehuda issura ka-amar. So presumably רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
actually saying no, there's a הלכה. halachah. And therefore
יהודה Yehudah they פסקן pasken this way, in גליל Galil they פסקן
pasken this way, and then that's relevant information. Because if I have
to know how to פסקן, pasken, I want to know how other
people are פסקן-ing. pasken Okay? And maybe that informs how I should
be פסקן-ing. pasken So the גמרא Gemara somehow reads into this description
of יהודה Yehudah and גליל Galil an approach that sees it's not
just a מנהג, minhag. but it's really different פסקים. psakim. And that's
why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, what do I care? It's all
just מנהג. minhag Okay, וסבר רבי יהודה, ve-savar Rabbi Yehuda, and therefore
it says the author of our משנה Mishna that speaks about יהודה
Yehudah and גליל Galil is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who sees it's
really a question of not just מנהג minhag but of פסק. psak.
There might be different פסקים, psakim, but it's an issue of פסק.
psak. And therefore that then leads into the בית שמאי Beit Shammai
and בית הלל Beit Hillel that are actually פסקן-ing pasken about the
night before or not the night before. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: וסבר רבי יהודה ארבעה עשר מותר בעשיית מלאכה?
ve-savar Rabbi Yehuda arba'ah asar mutar be-asiyat melachah?
Now can רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually hold, now regardless of what
we just said, although we just got through saying that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda holds that it's a הלכה halachah פסק, psak, but at
least there still is the position that there are some like in
יהודה Yehudah that hold that it's מותר on the morning. So the
גמרא Gemara. now questions whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could ever hold
that anybody says it's מותר in the morning. Why is that? והתניא,
ve-ha-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
המנכש בשלושה עשר. ha-menakesh be-shloshah asar.
You are like weeding your
wheat field on the thirteenth of ניסן. Nisan. Now the relevance here
is that it's going to become the fixed sixteenth of ניסן Nissan
and the עומר omer is going to be brought and the wheat
is going to be permissible. So you are there weeding your wheat
field on the thirteenth of ניסן. Nissan. ונעקר בידו venekar beyado and
a stalk of wheat got accidentally you pulled up in your hands.
So you want to replant it. But point is it has to
take root before the sixteenth in order for the עומר omer to
allow it to be eaten. So and it takes time for it
to take root. שותלה במקום הטיט, shotla bimkom hatit, so you replant
it in the place of like mud, ואין שותלה במקום הגריד ve-ein
shotla bimkom hagarid but not in the place of hard earth, 'cause
in the mud it will be able to take root. So now
why did it say the thirteenth? Because it takes three days to
take root. So the גמרא Gemara says: בשלושה עשר אין, בארבעה עשר
לא. bishlosha asar in, bearba'a asar lo. So only on the thirteenth,
not on the fourteenth. Now why not? מכדי, michdi, let's take a
look. סבירא ליה לרבי יהודה דאמר כל הרכבה שאינה קולטת בשלושה ימים
שוב אינה קולטת. svira leh le-rabbi yehuda de-amar kol harkava she-eina koletas
bishlosha yamim shuv eina koletas. We know רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
that any anything that doesn't take root, any planting or whatever that
doesn't take root in three days will not take root. So basically
within three days it'll take root. Fine. ואי סלקא דעתך ארבעה עשר
מותר בעשיית מלאכה, ve-i salka daitach arba'a asar mutar be-asiyas melacha, if
he held that you could do מלאכה melacha. on the fourteenth in
the morning and yet we like in יהודה Yehuda or something, so
למה לי שלושה עשר, lama li shlosha asar, why do you have
to give the example that it only works on the thirteenth? ואפילו
בארבעה עשר ve-afilu bearba'a asar it'll even work on the fourteenth if
you were doing this why if now you know if you were
you
know weeding...
here's the three days what is it? ארבעה עשר וחמישה עשר ומקצת
שישה עשר. arba'a asar ve-chamisha asar u-miktzas shisha asar. The גמרא Gemara
assumes that you don't need three full days. 14, 15, and a
little bit of the sixteenth. So if he didn't give that example,
presumably it's because you can't be doing מלאכה melacha, on the fourteenth.
So אמר רבא amar Rava בגליל שנו, bi-Galil shanu, which is an
easy answer maybe it wants to include even in the Galilee. There
are places in יהודה Yehuda that he could have given an example
the fourteenth, but he's talking about places where you can't do the
fourteenth if you're in the Galilee. So the גמרא Gemara's says ואיכא
לילה, ve-ika layla, how about the night before? אמר רב ששת כבית
שמאי, ke-Beis Shammai, always has all the stringencies. You're right. This statement
about doing weeding on the thirteenth assumes not on the fourteenth because
it's assuming the most מחמיר machmir position, בית שמאי Beis Shammai in
the Galilee. But it doesn't mean that there aren't other possibilities where
you could do it on the fourteenth. So גמרא Gemara says רב
אשי אמר לעולם כבית הלל, Rav Ashi amar le-olam ke-Beis Hillel, no,
could be like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. לפי שאין דרכם של בני
אדם לנכש בלילה, le-fi she-ein darkam shel benei adam lenakesh balayla, it
would be a very bizarre scenario to be out in your field
weeding in the night. But still basically the same answer. Right. But
still basically the same answer. Yes, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that
there are places that you're allowed to do it, but he wanted
to give a scenario even in the Galilee. רבינא אמר לעולם ביהודה,
Ravina amar le-olam bi-Yehuda, it could be in
יהודה, Yehuda, וחד מקצת היום ככולו אמרינן תרי מקצת היום ככולו לא
אמרינן. ve-chad miktzas hayom kekulo amrinan terei miktzas hayom kekulo la amrinan.
You only get one partial but you don't get two partial days.
You don't get the partial fourteenth, all the fifteenth, and the partial
sixteenth. Okay, when we say... so of course it's all funny it's
not like the plants know when it's a הלכה halachic day or
not. But okay anyway you only do that once you don't do
that twice so therefore you had to give the scenario of the
thirteenth regardless of the issue of מלאכה.
melacha, So the comparison between בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל...
Beis Hillel... so what's the reason? So the גמרא Gemara had it
much earlier if you remember way at the beginning in the מסכת
about you know to what degree do we have מקצת היום אסור
בעשיית מלאכה miktzas hayom assur be-asiyas melacha מקצת היום מותר, miktzas hayom
mutar, you know the idea of splitting a day and so on.
So
you know but you do have that by תענית, you have the
idea of splitting a day and beginning a תענית in the morning.
So בית שמאי Beis Shammai is basically being consistent like let's just
do a whole
day.
But if you're
worried about...
but that's the counter argument if the whole idea is to free
yourself to worry about הכנות hachanot and so on that must make
much more sense to focus on the morning. So good question of
how much how formalistic you're being about treating the whole day and
how much you are practically addressing you know where the pressing the
issue about the practical concerns. Okay, now let's continue. Now now it's
very funny because you do start with the בית הלל Beis Hillel
בית שמאי Beis Shammai and as the גמרא Gemara said talking in
more הלכה halachic language and less מנהג minhag language and talking about
פסח, Pesach, you know one of the that's one place where מנהג
minhag gets very much הלכה-סייזד halachisized is around you know the issue
of קטניות. kitniyot. But it is worth noting that you have it
in other places as well like practices during the ספירה, sefira, talking
again about the פסח Pesach time period of year. But a number
of those a small number are based on the גמרא Gemara but
a large number are מנהגים minhagim but they get פסקנד. paskened. Okay
so exactly the how מנהג minhag. starts becoming technical פסק הלכה psak
halacha is interesting. Some places it does, other places it does not.
Like even if you do כפרות, kaparos, somebody might say oh no
no we do it this way we don't do it that way
but nobody's going to say let's look up what the הלכה halacha
is about כפרות. kaparos. But they will say let's look up about
what the הלכה halacha is about קטניות kitniyot or about you know
or about מנהגי ספירה, minhagei sefira, right? So it's interesting which which
things get הלכה-סייזד halachisized or not. So let's take a look now
at this next משנה. That's my new word. רבי מאיר אומר Rebbi
Meir omer כל מלאכה שהתחיל בה קודם לארבעה עשר גומרה
בארבעה עשר. kol melacha she-hischil bah kodem le-arba'a asar gomra bearba'a asar.
If you began a מלאכה
and now it's interesting because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was the one
the גמרא Gemara. claimed was saying that it was דווקא מנהג davka
minhag and not a
הלכה halacha right? That's what the גמרא Gemara, said a minute ago.
Anyway here he's talking in more הלכה halachic language. If you began
the מלאכה before... on the 14th and even if you're in a
place which doesn't do מלאכה on the 14th you can finish it.
You can finish a מלאכה you're in the middle of. אבל לא
יתחיל בה בתחילה בארבעה עשר. Aval lo yatchil bah betchilah b'arba'ah asar.
Don't begin it at a new one on the 14th. אף על
פי שיכול לגומרה, Af al pi sheyachol l'gomrah, even if you have
the time to finish it don't start something new. But you do
have a special license even for places that don't do מלאכה on
the 14th you have a license to finish something that you started
earlier.
Like the ערב שבת Erev Shabbat משנה.
Yeah, right. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say ג' אומנויות
עושין מלאכה בערבי פסחים עד חצות. Shalosh umanuyot osin melacha b'arvei psachim
ad chatzot. No, it's not about starting beforehand or maybe
they're adding or if
they're rejecting but they have another point to make. They are saying
there are three craftsmen that can do מלאכה on ערב פסח Erev
Pesach regardless of your מנהג. minhag. And who are those? ואלו הן
V'elu hen חייטין chayatin tailors, והספרין, v'hasaparin, והספרין v'hasaparin
thank
you, ספרים saparim barbers, והכובסין v'hakovsin and launderers. Presumably all of these,
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara. explains, but presumably these are all
very pressing צורך המועד tzorech hamoed concerns.
No pun intended, right?
Pressing? No, not pressing. Anyway, that you need to do these things
right before the יום טוב. Yom Tov? But we'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara All right, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, no,
it's called why?
Yeah exactly,
exactly, exactly.
Wives are making them?
What? Yeah, this is talking about the professional aspect. Meaning when it
talks about מלאכה, it does not mean you can't make a fire
in your house on ערב פסח Erev Pesach because it's an איסור
to be עושה מלאכה. oseh melacha. We're talking about engaged in your
professional work. Okay, and therefore, so רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yossi bar Yehuda omer אף רצענין af ratzanin even shoemakers.
Okay, איבעיא להו. Ibayah lehu. Now the גמרא Gemara says we ask
לצורך המועד תנן, L'tzorech hamoed tnan, the end of the משנה certainly
emphasizes or presumably is related to צורך המועד. tzorech hamoed. But how
about the beginning where you can finish a מלאכה that you began
earlier? Is it only when that מלאכה is serving a purpose of
the for יום טוב? Yom Tov או שלא לצורך המועד אפילו מיגמר
נמי לא? O shelo l'tzorech hamoed afilu migmar nami lo? But if
it's not serving a יום טוב Yom Tov purpose you can't finish
even one that you had begun earlier. או דלמא O dilma or
would we say that you need two things, A לצורך המועד, l'tzorech
hamoed, B that you already began it? Or would we say that
you need one or the other? We'd be much more lenient. שלא
לצורך המועד תנן, Shelo l'tzorech hamoed tnan, that even when it's not
serving a יום טוב Yom Tov purpose you can end it if
you had already begun. אבל לצורך Aval l'tzorech but if you're doing
it for the purpose of יום טוב Yom Tov אתחולי מתחלינן Atchulei
matchilinan then you can even begin something, right? So that'd be, so
there's two issues: צורך tzorech and you already began. Do you need
both to allow or can either allow? תא שמע Ta shema come
and hear. אבל לא יתחיל בתחילה בארבעה עשר אפילו צלצול קטן. Aval
lo yatchil betchilah b'arba'ah asar afilu tzilzul katan. We have a ברייתא
that says don't begin, you know, a new מלאכה on the 14th
even a tiny little belt, אפילו שבכה קטנה afilu shvacha ktana even
a tiny little hat that you're going to make, you know, for
your head that takes only like it'll take an hour and you'll
do the whole thing. No, you can't do, you can't start new
מלאכה if at a place that you don't do מלאכה. של מאי
אפילו? Shel mai afilu? What does it mean even these things? לאו
אפילו הני דלצורך המועד מיגמר אין אתחולי לא? Lav afilu hanei d'tzorech
hamoed migmar in atchulei lo? Isn't it saying that even these things
which you're going to use on יום טוב Yom Tov, you can't
begin? So the גמרא Gemara says, which is funny, it seems like
the point is different and the גמרא's gemara going to say that.
לא. No, that's not what it's saying. לעולם דשלא לצורך מיגמר נמי
גמרינן. L'olam d'shelo l'tzorech migmar nami gamrinan. Doesn't this show you that
even something that's לצורך המועד tzorech hamoed you can only, you can't
begin it? And if it's שלא לצורך shelo l'tzorech then you can't
even complete? Isn't this the stricter read? That even these small things
of לצורך המועד tzorech hamoed you don't have license for? So the
גמרא says לא no, that's not what it's saying. לעולם דשלא לצורך
מיגמר נמי גמרינן. L'olam d'shelo l'tzorech migmar nami gamrinan. I could tell
you that even if שלא לצורך shelo l'tzorech you can complete. And
something that's לצורך המועד tzorech hamoed you can begin.
ומהי אפילו? U'mai afilu? So what does it mean even these things
like a little belt?
דהא דקעבדינן להו שלא לצורך המועד. D'ha d'ka avdinan lehu shelo l'tzorech
hamoed. So what's the חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש chiddush is אפילו הני
נמי דזוטרן אינהו afilu hanei nami d'zutran inhu even these things which
seems to be the point of the ברייתא that are so small,
that it takes you just an hour to do it, half hour
to do it. דסלקא דעתך אמינא אתחלתן זו היא גמר מלאכתן. D'salka
datch ach amina atchaltan zu hi gmar melachtan. I would say starting
it is like finishing it. You know, you'll get done with it
צ'יק צ'ק, chik chak, you know, it'll take me 20 minutes to
do it, why should it be a problem? No, לכתחילה מתחיל בהן
נמי לכתחילה L'chatchila matchil bahen nami l'chatchila
you can even start it because it's like finishing something else. קמשמע
לן דלא. Kamashma lan d'la. So we don't know yet the answer,
right? We know that the question is, do you need both criteria
in order to do it, לצורך המועד tzorech hamoed and finish, or
is either criteria enough? The point about the belt has nothing to
do with לצורך המועד. tzorech hamoed. The point about the belt is
that's considered starting not finishing even though it only takes you 20
minutes. תא שמע Ta shema come and hear. רבי
מאיר אומר כל מלאכה שהיא לצורך המועד. Rabbi Meir omer kol melacha
shehi l'tzorech hamoed. So here you have an explicit ברייתא. Rabbi Meir
says any מלאכה that is for the purpose of the מועד moed
גומרה בארבעה עשר gomrah b'arba'ah asar you can finish it on the
14th. So that's very clear that you need two criteria, right? You
need לצורך המועד tzorech hamoed and to finish it. אימתי בזמן שהתחיל
בה קודם ארבעה עשר Eimatai bizman shehit'chil bah kodem arba'ah asar when
you began earlier. אבל לא התחיל בה קודם ארבעה עשר לא יתחיל
בה בארבעה עשר. Aval lo hit'chil bah kodem arba'ah asar lo yatchil
bah b'arba'ah asar. And if you but you didn't start the begin
earlier, you can't begin it anew even though it's לצורך המועד. tzorech
hamoed. So this is a clear answer, right? That לצורך המועד tzorech
hamoed doesn't work, you need to have started before, you need both.
אפילו צלצול קטן אפילו שבכה קטנה Afilu tzilzul katan afilu shvacha ktana
even if it's a tiny little belt, even a tiny little hat.
Just the one that you can do צ'יק צ'ק, chick-chack, like a
little belt. And so the גמרא says לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed אין,
you see even when it comes to finishing, you can only do
it לצורך המועד, letzorech hamoed, שלא לצורך המועד shelo letzorech hamoed לא.
Not when it’s not לצורך המועד. letzorech hamoed. Seems to be pretty
darn clear. So the גמרא tries to get out of it. No,
הוא הדין אפילו שלא לצורך המועד נמי גמרינן. hu hadin afilu shelo
letzorech hamoed nami gamrinan. You know what, even though he mentioned לצורך
המועד, letzorech hamoed, you really could finish it even if it was
not לצורך המועד. letzorech hamoed. So why did he say לצורך המועד?
letzorech hamoed? וכמאן דאמר אפילו לצורך המועד מיגמר אין התחולי לא, u’keman
d’amar afilu letzorech hamoed migmar in hitchulei lo, to tell you that
even if it's לצורך המועד, letzorech hamoed, you can't start something new.
But in order to finish, right there you could finish regardless. So
the גמרא here is sort of laying out a third possibility. It's
saying it's true that
לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed by itself does not allow you and therefore
doesn't allow you to start something new. But if you started something
earlier, maybe the idea of finishing you'd always be allowed to finish
regardless of the לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed concern. So that's the one
question we have left to ask. Can we prove from this ברייתא
לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed doesn't do it by itself, but still the
question is maybe to be גומר, gomer, maybe that you could always
do? I think I actually skipped that line when I read the
earlier גמרא. Did I skip a line?
Yeah, there's the third option.
I guess the third option was in the גמרא, I forgot to
read it.
Yeah, there's three options in the גמרא. The
גמרא says לצורך המועד תנן אבל שלא לצורך המועד אפילו מיגמר נמי
לא, letzorech hamoed tnan aval shelo letzorech hamoed afilu migmar nami lo,
that you need לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed and to complete. או דילמא
שלא לצורך המועד תנן אבל לצורך התחולי מתחילין, o dilma shelo letzorech
hamoed tnan aval letzorech hitchulei matchilin, and option number two was when
it's either one is enough. And then there was option number three,
או דילמא בין לצורך המועד בין שלא לצורך מיגמר אין התחולי לא,
o dilma bein letzorech hamoed bein shelo letzorech migmar in hitchulei lo,
and option three was לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed is irrelevant, it's all
about finishing. So here the גמרא is suggesting option number three. Yes,
לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed doesn't work by itself, but maybe you always
need to start before, but maybe it's sufficient and the only factor
is if you started before and you could always finish regardless of
that issue of לצורך letzorech or not.
Started on the 13th, let’s say.
Yeah, start on the 13th or earlier. תא שמע. ta shema. So
that's what we have to figure out, if you start it earlier,
does it matter if it's לצורך המועד? letzorech hamoed? תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear. רבי מאיר אומר כל מלאכה שהיא לצורך המועד
גומרה בארבעה עשר ושאינו לצורך המועד אסור. Rabbi Meir omer kol melacha
shehi letzorech hamoed gomrah b’arba’ah asar v’sheino letzorech hamoed asur. And
so here it's going to be black and white. Any מלאכה that's
לצורך המועד, letzorech hamoed, you can finish on the
14th, and if it's not לצורך המועד, letzorech hamoed, then you can't
finish it on the 14th. So okay, pretty clear, you need to
be two criteria: you need it to be begun earlier and לצורך
המועד. letzorech hamoed. ועושין מלאכה בארבעה עשר עד חצות במקום שנהגו. v’osin
melacha b’arba’ah asar ad chatzot b’makom shenahagu. And
by the way, that's only in the time that it's forbidden, but
there are places where you can do it the whole morning if
that's your מנהג.
minhag, Right, as long as you're finishing something לצורך המועד. letzorech hamoed.
No, meaning when it's אסור, this will be an allowance. But there
are places where you don't need an allowance, where anyway it's מותר
in the morning, and you need an allowance maybe in the afternoon
but not in the morning. So מקום שנהגו אין לא נהגו לא.
makom shenahagu in lo nahagu lo. So you see, in a place
that you don't have the מנהג, minhag it's basically אסור unless you
have that specific allowance that we just said. ושמע מינה לצורך המועד
אין שלא לצורך המועד לא שמע מינה. u’shma mina letzorech hamoed in
shelo letzorech hamoed lo shma mina. So it's very clear there, it's
only allowed if it started earlier and it is לצורך המועד. letzorech
hamoed. Now that is during a time period where your מנהג minhag
is not to do מלאכה. So we're talking about the places where
they do not do מלאכה in the morning. Okay, let's just wrap
this up. וחכמים אומרים שלש אומנויות, v’Chachamim omrim shalosh umanuyot, and the
Rabbis say besides this issue of starting earlier, which now we understand
is two things: starting earlier and לצורך המועד, letzorech hamoed, they have
a blanket allowance for three professions which to us seem or maybe
four also very much pressing לצורך המועד. letzorech hamoed. תנא, we taught
in a ברייתא: החייטין. hachayatin.
Now the ברייתא gives the reason for this not directly of the
לצורך המועד letzorech hamoed but more because there are other places where
we're lenient about these people doing מלאכה. We understand how important their
work is that we are lenient in other places about them doing
מלאכה, not obviously like שבת and יום טוב, but we will see
חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. החייטין, hachayatin, why do they allow tailors? שכן
הדיוט תופר כדרכו בחולו של מועד. sheken hedyot tofer k’darko b’cholo shel
moed. We allow a person to do some home stitching on חול
המועד. Chol Hamoed. So there are places where we're lenient about sewing,
so we'll be lenient here even in places where it's the מנהג
minhag, not to do
מלאכה. הספרין והכובסין שכן הבאים ממדינת הים והיוצאים מבית האסורים מספרים ומכבסים
בחולו של מועד. hasaparim v’hakovsin sheken habaim mimedinat hayam v’hayotzim mibeit ha’asurim
mesaprim umachabsim b’cholo shel moed. Because people that get out of prison
or come from overseas, we allow them to get a haircut and
to launder their clothes. And that clearly is based on the idea
of כבוד הרגל. kvod haregal. But the גמרא here is not directly
saying that it's כבוד הרגל kvod haregal that's operative, it's saying since
there are leniencies in other places, we're also lenient here. This whole
thing is a מנהג, this whole thing is clearly not as strict
as חול המועד Chol Hamoed even in the period when it's forbidden.
Now in מועד קטן, Moed Katan, these things are there as an
איסור, right?
Right, מועד קטן Moed Katan these things are clearly אסור except for
these exceptions. What we do is we take these very exceptional cases
and make them into rules about this whole profession.
Yes, ערב פסח. erev pesach. רבי יהושע בן בתירא Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Betira אומר omer אף הרצענים, af haratze'anim, he says even the shoemakers,
why שכן sheken עולי רגלים olei regalim מתקנים מנעליהם metaknim man'aleihem בחול
המועד, bechol hamoed, because we allow the עולי רגלים olei regalim to
fix their shoes I mean they've been walking the entire trip or
whatever travel, they don't have time to fix their shoes on ערב
יום טוב, erev yom tov, we give them the allowance to do
it on חול המועד. chol hamoed. So here too we give the
allowance. Now, במאי קמיפלגי, bemai kamiflagi, what's the debate about the shoemakers?
מר סבר למדין תחלת מלאכה מסוף מלאכה, mar savar lemedin techilat melacha
misof melacha, that we learn the beginning מלאכה, meaning from you know
making shoes, from the end of the מלאכה, from the fact that
we allow you to fix shoes. ומר סבר אין למדין תחלת מלאכה
מסוף מלאכה, umar savar ein lemedin techilat melacha misof melacha, yes there's
cases where we allow you to fix shoes but we do not
ever allow you to make shoes and therefore, and therefore, we cannot,
we don't, we won't allow it here. But again you could have
just said it's all based on the צורך המועד tzorech hamoed aspects
of this, it's interesting that the גמרא frames it in the terms
of there are other places where we are lenient. So we will
end here sadly, we still are a little bit behind, I don't
know how we're going to make it up, we won't allow Michael
to ask anything. No time.